<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://alainmauri.eu/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://alainmauri.eu/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-09-15T16:57:26+01:00</updated><id>https://alainmauri.eu/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Alain Mauri</title><subtitle>First draft of my new personal website</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Thoughts in random order</title><link href="https://alainmauri.eu/2024/08/26/random-thoughts/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thoughts in random order" /><published>2024-08-26T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-08-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://alainmauri.eu/2024/08/26/random-thoughts</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alainmauri.eu/2024/08/26/random-thoughts/"><![CDATA[<p>AI-generated images are a problem, no more or less than “natural” ones. Can we determine whether an image is authentic or not? If someone claims an image is fake - e.g., Trump regarding a Kamala Harris rally -
can we produce documentation to prove its authenticity? And if so, will others be willing to accept the truth, or will they continue to believe what suits them best?
Italian researcher Walter Quattrociocchi, in an article for the financial newspaper <a href="https://www.ilsole24ore.com/art/armarsi-contro-fake-news-strumenti-il-prebunking-e-debunking-AGTHB8W">Il Sole 24 ore</a>, explains that debunking doesn’t work, mostly because people stick to their mental models
even when confronted with the truth. This is where prebunking becomes useful.
Prebunking, also known as inoculation theory in communication studies, is a proactive approach to combating misinformation.
The goal of prebunking is to equip people with the skills to spot false and misleading information online before they encounter it, thereby preempting manipulation.
This method works by exposing individuals to weakened forms of misinformation and teaching them how to identify and counter deceptive tactics.</p>

<p>Key aspects of prebunking include:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Education: Teaching critical thinking skills and common manipulation techniques used in misinformation.</li>
  <li>Exposure: Presenting mild doses of misinformation along with explanations of why it’s misleading.</li>
  <li>Practice: Allowing individuals to apply their new knowledge in controlled scenarios.</li>
  <li>Reinforcement: Regularly updating and reinforcing these skills as misinformation tactics evolve.</li>
</ol>

<p>By implementing prebunking strategies, the aim is to make online users more resilient to being misled in the future.
This approach acknowledges that prevention is often more effective than cure when it comes to battling the spread of misinformation in our digital age.</p>

<p>I’ve been back to Italy with the whole family after two years. Many things have changed, and I feel I belong to a different place now.
But still, when I come here, many sweet memories come to my mind, and I start questioning my past choices.
I guess it’s normal, given that I moved to the UK for two main reasons: better job opportunities for a Rubyist and putting some distance between myself and all the pressures my former life was
putting on me. 
Anyway, seeing what my kids have become and the happiness in my wife’s eyes is enough to say that our life has improved a lot,
despite Brexit and all the xenophobic rhetoric that comes from the British far right.</p>

<p>I want to learn how to solve a Rubik’s cube! :smile: I remember when I was a kid, back in the 80s, I had a Rubik’s cube and after scrambling it, I detached all the coloured stickers and
put them back in the right order, pretending I had solved it!</p>

<p>I’m reading “Ruby under a Microscope” again. Sometimes I need to refresh my understanding of the language, and I think that I know more about Ruby than I do about Rails.
This hasn’t always been valued during interviews. What fascinates me is the way the language handles different scenarios, such as <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">include</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">extend</code>, and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">prepend</code>,
the algorithms used to parse the code, and generally all the internal mechanisms that make my life as a developer easier.</p>

<hr />

<h4 id="things-i-like---in-random-order">Things I like - in random order</h4>

<p>Some other pictures I recently took:</p>

<p><br />
<img src="https://pxscdn.com/public/m/_v2/424813098022428933/3781ba7d4-1bb9dc/8S7jdImacpHV/VPQAShFmJHjrIN6kSm5rsgAEpqHGsNxA9IEYmgIf.jpg" alt="a woman smiling while walking the dogs in Brighton" class="post-image" />
<br />
<br />
<img src="https://pxscdn.com/public/m/_v2/424813098022428933/530d83cd3-f15549/ShUL7h8BaWYq/b5eRHVRH7oE3gvjTsAuXkrwGUOmNmbb2OreasATo.jpg" alt="a photographer with some dancers posing for him in kelham island sheffield" class="post-image" />
<br />
<br /></p>

<p>:heart: I’ve tried many IDEs in my career but I always come back to Lunarvim or Emacs :heart:</p>

<hr />

<h4 id="todays-links">Today’s Links</h4>

<p>Prebunking with <a href="https://prebunking.withgoogle.com">Google</a></p>

<p>You need just 19 words to provide <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8lfQGSV47Y8">wise feedback</a> from Daniel Pink <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Pinkcast</code></p>

<p>Microsoft refuses to patch multiple flaws in Microsoft macOS apps <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/08/19/cisco_talos_microsoft_macos/">The Register</a></p>

<p>Who uses LLM <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/08/13/who_uses_llm_prompt_injection/">prompt injection?</a></p>

<p>The Obamas’ <a href="https://slate.com/news-and-politics/2024/08/barack-obama-crowd-size-michelle-obama-black-jobs-dnc-speech.html">real superpower</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Wildeng</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[AI-generated images are a problem, no more or less than “natural” ones. Can we determine whether an image is authentic or not? If someone claims an image is fake - e.g., Trump regarding a Kamala Harris rally - can we produce documentation to prove its authenticity? And if so, will others be willing to accept the truth, or will they continue to believe what suits them best? Italian researcher Walter Quattrociocchi, in an article for the financial newspaper Il Sole 24 ore, explains that debunking doesn’t work, mostly because people stick to their mental models even when confronted with the truth. This is where prebunking becomes useful. Prebunking, also known as inoculation theory in communication studies, is a proactive approach to combating misinformation. The goal of prebunking is to equip people with the skills to spot false and misleading information online before they encounter it, thereby preempting manipulation. This method works by exposing individuals to weakened forms of misinformation and teaching them how to identify and counter deceptive tactics.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Busy Bee, balancing work, life and photography</title><link href="https://alainmauri.eu/2024/05/27/what-i-am-doing/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Busy Bee, balancing work, life and photography" /><published>2024-05-27T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-05-27T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://alainmauri.eu/2024/05/27/what-i-am-doing</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alainmauri.eu/2024/05/27/what-i-am-doing/"><![CDATA[<p>In these past weeks, I haven’t had as much time to write as I’d like, given that work has been really demanding.
This is something I’m hoping to create more space for in the coming weeks. But even with a busy schedule,
I’ve been able to find moments to move forward with my French and Friulian studies, mostly during the evenings.</p>

<p>I’ve also gotten into the habit of carrying my camera whenever I walk somewhere. 
There’s always something worth capturing, and it’s a great way to experiment and improve my photography skills.
Whether it’s mastering camera settings or post-processing with Procreate,
I’m constantly learning. Speaking of Procreate, it’s been a blast playing around with adding color to black and white photos.
It’s taken me to some unexpected places creatively, like this one I’ve posted on my Pixelfed account:<br />
<br />
<img src="https://pxscdn.com/public/m/_v2/424813098022428933/7321b8e85-c3df53/HeUeZiWYek2E/VNrIqj84Yh1xAsvQkCLioMehh53ywjH3IZ6o56Im.jpg" alt="some houses in crookes road sheffield black and white picture" class="post-image" />
<br /></p>

<p>On the developer side of things, Brighton Ruby is approaching and I’m lucky enough to have a ticket!<br />
Thanks again to <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/salwan-shimoun-43a0b8228">Sawan</a>.
It looks like a fantastic year for the conference, with so many interesting speakers.
I’m particularly looking forward to hearing from Nadia Odunayio, the developer behind The Story Graph (a fantastic alternative to Goodreads!), 
and Chris Oliver, the mind behind Go Rails. I’m also eager to learn more about Ruby Ractors from Daniel Vartanov’s talk. 
Having some experience with Goroutines, I’m curious about the similarities between the two for parallel processing.</p>

<h4 id="my-relation-with-llms">My relation with LLMs</h4>

<p>So far I’ve developed a cautios relationship with LLMs, sometimes I use them but I’ve got in the habit of checking the information provided, given the
frequent hallucinations they have. Still, although they are sometimes useful, I don’t feel that scraping the Internet to feed them without paying anything to
the people that crafted all that content is fair. In my eyes these companies just another wave of capitalists that are trying to make money by literally
stealing someone else’s work. Gary Marcus on <a href="https://x.com/GaryMarcus/status/1744362345403392510">X - Twitter</a> said it well, talking about OpenAI call for
copyright exemption to “save” ChatGPT:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Rough Translation: We won’t get fabulously rich if you don’t let us steal, so please don’t make stealing a crime!</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I think that’s the right time to put some regulation in place, we cannot let these people do whatever they want without any kind of rule, they need to be
accountable for any kind of damage their activity can cause.</p>

<hr />

<h4 id="things-i-like---in-random-order">Things I like - in random order</h4>

<p>This time I just want to post some pictures I’m really proud of:</p>

<p><br />
<img src="https://pxscdn.com/public/m/_v2/424813098022428933/7321b8e85-c3df53/nBzo0vhN1wlg/6NuzDIkzXbxXxXOZ2LqfcFTL2jDh2qEFUobiQIdd.jpg" alt="barkers pool in sheffield, photo taken at dusk with the camera sitting on a marble bench reflecting some images" class="post-image" />
<br />
<br />
<img src="https://pxscdn.com/public/m/_v2/424813098022428933/7321b8e85-c3df53/nssuu91hRBMz/H0sZD3ddVokltUyezlFZ828tijHGQV3pni6R79Wu.jpg" class="post-image" /></p>

<hr />

<h4 id="todays-links">Today’s Links</h4>

<p>How far Trump <a href="https://time.com/6972021/donald-trump-2024-election-interview/">would go</a></p>

<p>Open AI will use Reddit Post to train ChatGPT <a href="https://arstechnica.com/ai/2024/05/openai-will-use-reddit-posts-to-train-chatgpt-under-new-deal/">Ars Tehcnica</a></p>

<p>An Introduction to ractors in Ruby on <a href="https://blog.appsignal.com/2022/08/24/an-introduction-to-ractors-in-ruby.html">Appsignal</a></p>

<p>Slack users horrified to discover messages used for AI training <a href="https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2024/05/slack-defends-default-opt-in-for-ai-training-on-chats-amid-user-outrage/">Ars Technica</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Wildeng</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In these past weeks, I haven’t had as much time to write as I’d like, given that work has been really demanding. This is something I’m hoping to create more space for in the coming weeks. But even with a busy schedule, I’ve been able to find moments to move forward with my French and Friulian studies, mostly during the evenings.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Rise of the machines, are software engineers next?</title><link href="https://alainmauri.eu/2024/04/09/ai-big-replacement/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rise of the machines, are software engineers next?" /><published>2024-04-09T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-04-09T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://alainmauri.eu/2024/04/09/ai-big-replacement</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alainmauri.eu/2024/04/09/ai-big-replacement/"><![CDATA[<p>Watching the rise of different tools that “can function as a fully autonomous software engineer”(<a href="https://easywithai.com/ai-developer-tools/devin/">Devin Introduction</a>) I’ve started thinking about the future of my job as a software engineer and obviously one big question came into my mind:</p>

<p>Will my job be replaced by LLMs or is this simply a new tool to learn and improve my daily workflow? <br />
I’m honestly worried about this and I started researching a bit around the argument and what I’ve found is not so encouraging at all.<br />
Take a look at what Jensen Huang Nvidia CEO <a href="https://twitter.com/Carnage4Life/status/1761483377365152234">said</a>. Now, should we stop teaching Computer Science because AI will generate all the code we want by using natural language? Honestly, should we take the word of someone with a vested financial interest? I don’t think so, however his words are outlining a common trend that’s well explained in this post by <a href="https://www.baldurbjarnason.com/2024/the-one-about-the-web-developer-job-market/">Baldur Bjarnason</a> which is a long one to summarize but let me put it in plain and simple words:<br />
As software engineers we are well paid and this, in the modern tech - and not only - corporate world is something that needs to be fixed with every means, and honestly this is what management believes: Read this <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/cscareerquestions/comments/1axlbub/executive_leadership_believes_llms_will_replace/">Reddit</a> thread quoted in Bjarnason’s post, among other things.</p>

<p>The most positive approach I found so far is this by <a href="https://thenewstack.io/code-in-context-how-ai-can-help-improve-our-documentation/">Jon Udell</a> he thinks that LLms will help us understanding existing code rather than writing it, because of their “ability” to recognise patterns and summarise the findings. In his eyes this should improve the quality of the documentation and the overall quality of the code itself, that will for sure still be written by humans.</p>

<p>Now what should I do? Well, before moving to the Uk I was freelancing and I never put my eggs in one basket so I will try to diversify my knowledge again. By diversifying my skills with languages like Rust and Crystal, honing my writing abilities, and pursuing scrum master training - my company required it. What I do hope though is that human expertise in problem-solving and creative thinking will continue to be valuable in this field, despite the push to automate everything.</p>

<hr />

<h4 id="things-i-like---in-random-order">Things I like - in random order</h4>

<p>I honestly love my second hand Canon EOS 100D because I’m finally able to experiment with photography in a proper way, learning what different settings are doing and boosting my creativity. Digital photography for sure helped photographers and not replaced them and this is what tech innovation means to me.<br />
Here are two pictures that I took with it:
<br />
<br />
<img src="/images/burned-car-carcass.jpg" alt="a burned car carcass found in a park in sheffield" class="post-image" />
<br />
<br />
<img src="/images/grass-blades.jpg" alt="grass blades in the wind" class="post-image" />
<br /></p>

<hr />

<h4 id="todays-links">Today’s Links</h4>

<p>The uncanny music of Slack Huddles on <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/slack-huddle-hold-music-secret-history/">Wired</a><br />
Texas is replacing human graders with AI <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2024/4/10/24126206/texas-staar-exam-graders-ai-automated-scoring-engine">The Verge</a>
Own Your Web <a href="https://buttondown.email/ownyourweb/archive/issue-13/">Issue 13</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Wildeng</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Watching the rise of different tools that “can function as a fully autonomous software engineer”(Devin Introduction) I’ve started thinking about the future of my job as a software engineer and obviously one big question came into my mind:]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Finding balance, The Web and HTML’s Power</title><link href="https://alainmauri.eu/2024/02/18/finding-balance-html-power/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Finding balance, The Web and HTML’s Power" /><published>2024-02-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://alainmauri.eu/2024/02/18/finding-balance-html-power</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alainmauri.eu/2024/02/18/finding-balance-html-power/"><![CDATA[<p>Despite my best efforts to consistently publish blog posts, I’ve found it challenging to maintain the required level of commitment. Opting for the latter, I’ve decided to write a post whenever inspiration strikes, sharing thoughts that hold personal meaning rather than aiming solely for a wide audience. Writing is an enjoyable endeavor for me, serving as a way to capture discoveries, experiences, and thoughts in a cohesive order.</p>

<p>In my current job, I predominantly work on backend applications with occasional forays into frontend development. Despite the shift, I still find joy in working on simple HTML and CSS projects. Recently, I stumbled upon a fascinating book by <a href="https://htmlandcssbook.com">John Duckett</a> in a charity shop, published in 2011. Despite its age, the book encapsulates fundamental web development knowledge in an aesthetically pleasing format.</p>

<p>Beyond its technical insights, the book has become a valuable visual aid, helping me understand how different elements fit into a webpage. It’s not just about the technicalities; the book has inspired me to appreciate the artistry in web development. Although I often turn to search engines for quick answers, there’s a unique satisfaction in slowing down and leafing through a physical book.</p>

<p>Speaking of which, let me delve into the book’s influence on my work. The way it’s structured has not only enriched my technical understanding but also provided a visual framework for organizing elements on a page. This, coupled with the nostalgia of using a tangible resource, has added a unique layer to my learning experience.</p>

<p>HTML, a language I consider powerful, has granted countless individuals the ability to express themselves on the vast canvas of the internet. Despite the ongoing debate about whether HTML is a programming language, its significance in enabling digital expression cannot be overstated. As I continue my journey in web development, I find solace in the simplicity and potency of HTML, a language that empowers creativity on the worldwide web.</p>

<p>Here are two examples from the book:<br />
<br />
<img src="/images/how-the-web-works.png" alt="an infographic about how the web works with diagram and text" class="post-image" />
<br />
<br />
<img src="/images/pages-structure.png" alt="an image about how to structure a web page" class="post-image" />
<br />
<br /></p>

<p><br /></p>

<p>I just discovered - from an account I follow on Mastodon - that in Japan you can find magazines whose subjects are Yakuza families and it looks like the average Japanese salary man enjoys them quite a lot as a way to escape the day to day life - scroll to find the link to the article.</p>

<hr />

<h4 id="things-i-like---in-random-order">Things I like - in random order</h4>

<p>I love the snow and my backyard looks beautiful with it.<br />
This is a picture I took during the last snowstorm<br />
<br />
<img src="/images/backyard-snow.jpeg" alt="My backyard covered by snow" class="post-image" />
<br /></p>

<hr />

<h4 id="todays-links">Today’s Links</h4>

<p>The strange world of Yakuza fan <a href="https://publishingperspectives.com/2009/10/the-strange-world-of-yakuza-fan-magazines/">magazines</a><br />
<a href="https://www.rorvswild.com/blog/2023/everyday-performance-rules-for-ruby-on-rails-developers">Every day performance</a> for Ruby Developers<br />
mruby 3.3.0 has been released and supports the <a href="https://mruby.org/releases/2024/02/14/mruby-3.3.0-released.html">Nintendo Wii</a> <br />
The Apple Macintosh turned 40 this past January, here is <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/01/24/apple-mac-man/">Mr. Macintosh</a> <br />
The writer goes to an annual tech conference and he left with mixed feelings <a href="https://www.rollingstone.com/culture/culture-features/ai-companies-advocates-cult-1234954528/">The Cult of AI</a><br />
The Sega <a href="https://www.smspower.org/SegaAI/Index">AI Computer</a> was released in 1986. The company promised that natural language processing was available through their Prolog interpreter.</p>]]></content><author><name>Wildeng</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Despite my best efforts to consistently publish blog posts, I’ve found it challenging to maintain the required level of commitment. Opting for the latter, I’ve decided to write a post whenever inspiration strikes, sharing thoughts that hold personal meaning rather than aiming solely for a wide audience. Writing is an enjoyable endeavor for me, serving as a way to capture discoveries, experiences, and thoughts in a cohesive order.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ruby Insights, Learning Journey, and Cultural Exploration</title><link href="https://alainmauri.eu/2024/01/19/ruby-learning-cultural-exploration/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ruby Insights, Learning Journey, and Cultural Exploration" /><published>2024-01-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://alainmauri.eu/2024/01/19/ruby-learning-cultural-exploration</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alainmauri.eu/2024/01/19/ruby-learning-cultural-exploration/"><![CDATA[<p>While reading the <a href="https://kddnewton.com/2023/11/30/advent-of-prism-part-0">Advent of Prism</a> about the new Ruby parser that’s now been integrated into runtimes and tooling I came across something that I had overlooked:</p>

<p><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Numbers such as 010 are treated by Ruby as Octal by default</code></p>

<p>I completely forgot about this, mainly because I don’t often use octals - honestly never - so I did a small research about it and the reason behind this can be traced back to the C programming language and according to this Stack Overflow <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/11483216/why-are-leading-zeroes-used-to-represent-octal-numbers#11483339">post</a> it’s a convention that’s been introduce by [B Programming language](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/B_(programming_language)
 The historical reason behind treating numbers with a leading 0 as octal in some programming languages, including Ruby, can be traced back to the influence of the C programming language.</p>

<p>In the C programming language, a numeric literal with a leading 0 is treated as an octal constant. This behavior was likely introduced to provide a convenient way to represent octal values directly in the source code. For example, in C:</p>
<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>int octalNumber = 0123;  // This represents the octal value of 83
</code></pre></div></div>
<p>a similar behaviour can be found in C++. C#, Java, JavaScript.</p>

<p>I’ve started learning touch typing, so far it’s been quite challenging and it needs a lot of practice and discipline. I’m honestly enjoying it and is likely one of those skills that could boost my self confidence. I’m following the free lessons at <a href="https://www.edclub.com/sportal/program-3.game">Typing Club</a></p>

<p>I’m making progress in my French studies on Duolingo and I’ve noticed that I’m now able to understand most of the material I’m reading as an aid to my lessons. Obviously I’m still at a beginner level and mainly using present tense. The journey is still long, but so far it’s been really interesting.
Talking about languages I’ve also enrolled in a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Friulian_language">Friulian</a> course. It’s a minority language spoken in the Italian region I’m from and even if I can understand it, like most of the people living there, I can’t speak it properly. Now is the time to fill this gap. It’s part of my culture and in some way it had influenced who I currently am, so definitely worth learning it.</p>

<p>I find the new iPhone journal app quite nice. It prompts some cool suggestions and it’s a way to keep track what you’ve done during the day or more than one if you’re not using it daily. I believe journalling is something than can help organise your thoughts and reflections at a moment in time.</p>

<hr />

<h4 id="things-i-like---in-random-order">Things I like - in random order</h4>

<p>If you’re looking for a definition of beauty here it is:</p>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pietà_(Michelangelo)">Pietà di Michelangelo</a>
<br />
<img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/a/a7/Michelangelo's_Pieta_5450.jpg" alt="a picture of michelangelo pieta" class="post-image" />
<br />
<br /></p>

<hr />

<h4 id="todays-links">Today’s Links</h4>

<p>Why all the coffee shops looks the same on <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/news/2024/jan/16/the-tyranny-of-the-algorithm-why-every-coffee-shop-looks-the-same">The Guardian</a></p>

<p>Why more Brits feel unhappy at work <a href="https://www.mirror.co.uk/news/uk-news/blue-monday-here-more-brits-31850068">Blue Monday</a></p>

<p>OpenAI changes policy to allow <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/01/12/openai-changes-policy-to-allow-military-applications/">military operations</a></p>

<p>The Boeing’s plug door <a href="https://slate.com/technology/2024/01/boeing-737-max-9-plug-door-alaska-airlines.html">fiasco</a></p>

<p>A Github repository about principles and patterns for software developers <a href="https://github.com/dwmkerr/hacker-laws">Hacker Laws</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Wildeng</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[While reading the Advent of Prism about the new Ruby parser that’s now been integrated into runtimes and tooling I came across something that I had overlooked: Numbers such as 010 are treated by Ruby as Octal by default]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Blocks Procs and Lambdas</title><link href="https://alainmauri.eu/2023/12/28/blocks-procs-and-lambdas/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Blocks Procs and Lambdas" /><published>2023-12-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://alainmauri.eu/2023/12/28/blocks-procs-and-lambdas</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alainmauri.eu/2023/12/28/blocks-procs-and-lambdas/"><![CDATA[<p>Ruby has three types of anonymous functions: Blocks, Procs and Lambdas.</p>

<h5 id="-block-">====== Block ======</h5>

<p>Blocks are anonymous pieces of code that are not objects but can be passed to methods for execution. An example is the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">map</code> method from the <a href="https://ruby-doc.org/core-3.0.2/Enumerable.html#method-i-map">Enumerable mixin</a>, which accepts and executes a block of code:</p>

<div class="language-ruby highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="p">[</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">2</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">3</span><span class="p">].</span><span class="nf">map</span> <span class="p">{</span> <span class="o">|</span><span class="n">x</span><span class="o">|</span> <span class="n">x</span><span class="o">*</span> <span class="mi">2</span> <span class="p">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Methods explicitly or implicitly accept blocks:</p>

<div class="language-ruby highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">method_implicit</span>
  <span class="nb">puts</span> <span class="s2">"Starting the method"</span>
  <span class="k">yield</span> <span class="k">if</span> <span class="nb">block_given?</span>
  <span class="nb">puts</span> <span class="s2">"ending"</span>
<span class="k">end</span>

<span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">method_explicit</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="o">&amp;</span><span class="n">block</span><span class="p">)</span>
  <span class="nb">puts</span> <span class="s2">"Starting explicit"</span>
  <span class="n">block</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">call</span>
  <span class="nb">puts</span> <span class="s2">"ending explicit"</span>
<span class="k">end</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>In the first case, the method uses <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">yield</code> to execute the block if provided. In the second case, the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&amp;block</code> syntax indicates that the method expects a block as an argument.
One more thing to remember is that when the block is executed the control passes to it and returns to the method when the block has finished its execution.</p>

<h5 id="-proc-">====== Proc ======</h5>

<p>Unlike blocks, Proc - from the <a href="https://ruby-doc.org/3.3.0/Proc.html">Ruby docs</a> - are objects which encapsulate blocks of code. They can be stored in a variable, passed to a method or to other Procs. Proc are closures,meaning they remember and can use the entire context in which they were created. For instance:</p>

<div class="language-ruby highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="n">pow_two</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="no">Proc</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">new</span> <span class="p">{</span> <span class="o">|</span><span class="n">x</span><span class="o">|</span> <span class="n">x</span><span class="o">**</span><span class="mi">2</span> <span class="p">}</span>
<span class="n">pow_two</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">call</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">3</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="c1"># Output: 9</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Procs retain access to variables in their creation context:</p>

<div class="language-ruby highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">create_proc</span>
  <span class="n">local_variable</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="s2">"I am from the original scope"</span>
  <span class="nb">proc</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="no">Proc</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">new</span> <span class="k">do</span>
    <span class="nb">puts</span> <span class="n">local_variable</span>
  <span class="k">end</span>
  <span class="nb">proc</span>
<span class="k">end</span>

<span class="c1"># Create a Proc in one scope</span>
<span class="n">my_proc</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">create_proc</span>

<span class="c1"># Call the Proc in a different scope</span>
<span class="n">my_proc</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">call</span> <span class="c1"># Output: I'm from the original scope</span>
</code></pre></div></div>
<p>It’s worth mentioning that this could potentially lead to troubles if the creation context is not available anymore or has changed such in the case of serialization/deserialization or if used in a different object or class context.</p>

<p>Consider now this example:</p>

<div class="language-ruby highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">another_proc</span>
  <span class="n">local_var</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="s2">"I'm local"</span>
  <span class="nb">proc</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="no">Proc</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">new</span> <span class="p">{</span> <span class="k">return</span> <span class="n">local_var</span> <span class="p">}</span>
  <span class="nb">proc</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">call</span>
  <span class="k">return</span> <span class="s2">"another one"</span>
<span class="k">end</span>

<span class="n">irb</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">main</span><span class="p">):</span><span class="mo">053</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="o">&gt;</span> <span class="nb">puts</span> <span class="n">another_proc</span>
<span class="no">I</span><span class="err">'</span><span class="n">m</span> <span class="n">local</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Procs do not pass back control to the calling method but immediately return.  <br />
They are generous about accepting arguments. Missing ones will be fit with <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">nil</code>, single Array will be deconstructed if having multiple arguments and no errors will be raised on extra ones.</p>

<h5 id="-lambda-">====== Lambda ======</h5>

<p>Lambdas are objects of the Proc class created using the <a href="https://ruby-doc.org/3.3.0/Kernel.html#method-i-lambda">kernel#lambda</a> semantics. They are stricter with passed arguments compared to regular Procs. Notably, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">return</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">break</code> in a lambda exits the lambda and returns control to the calling function:</p>

<div class="language-ruby highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">lambda_method</span>
  <span class="n">local</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="s2">"I'm local"</span>
  <span class="n">lam</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nb">lambda</span> <span class="p">{</span><span class="k">return</span> <span class="n">local</span> <span class="p">}</span>
  <span class="nb">puts</span> <span class="n">lam</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">call</span>
  <span class="nb">puts</span> <span class="s2">"end"</span>
<span class="k">end</span>

<span class="n">lambda_method</span> <span class="c1"># Output: I'm local end</span>
</code></pre></div></div>
<p>Understanding when to employ each of these constructs is crucial for writing clean and efficient Ruby code. Blocks are excellent for short, one-off operations, Procs offer encapsulation and context retention, while Lambdas provide a balance of strict argument handling and the familiarity of Proc behavior.</p>

<hr />

<h4 id="things-i-like---in-random-order">Things I like - in random order</h4>

<p>The Astronomy Picture of the Day is something beautiful: <a href="https://apod.nasa.gov/apod/ap231225.html">Cathedral, Mountain, Moon</a></p>

<p>Probably a lot of people started using a computer with Windows installed - a stock <a href="https://archive.org/details/win3_stock">Windows 3.1</a> on the Internet Archive</p>

<p>What an extraordinary historical archive: <a href="https://clp.bbcrewind.co.uk/">BBC Computer Literacy Project 1980 - 1989</a></p>

<p><br />
The Acorn BBC Micro<br />
<br />
<img src="/images/acorn-bbc-micro.jpg" alt="the acorn bbc micro computer" class="post-image" />
<br />
<br /></p>

<hr />

<h4 id="todays-links">Today’s Links</h4>

<blockquote>
  <p>They say that electronic mail tends to be informal in style (as opposed to written mail) and makes people bolder. This encourages those who wouldn’t dare to say something direct to your face (and who don’t have anything serious enough to say to commit it to a formal, written memo) to send you “brazen” messages.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Sounds familiar? An old article about email and conventional post - 1983 <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2023/dec/01/could-email-undermine-conventional-post-1983">Could electronic mail undermine conventional post?</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.ruby-lang.org/en/news/2023/12/25/ruby-3-3-0-released/">Ruby 3.3</a> has been released with some really interesting additions to the language</p>

<p>The Most Important Unsolved Problem in Computer Science <a href="https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/the-most-important-unsolved-problem-in-computer-science/">Scientific American</a></p>

<p>Good news you didn’t hear about <a href="https://futurecrunch.com/goodnews2023/">Futurecrunch</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Wildeng</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Ruby has three types of anonymous functions: Blocks, Procs and Lambdas.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Sacred Graal of Editors</title><link href="https://alainmauri.eu/2023/12/23/editor-sacred-graal/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Sacred Graal of Editors" /><published>2023-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://alainmauri.eu/2023/12/23/editor-sacred-graal</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alainmauri.eu/2023/12/23/editor-sacred-graal/"><![CDATA[<p>In my last post I said that I wanted to be more technical and so be it. But in a different way and not “so technical”: I won’t talk about classes, methods, modules, mixin or some other Ruby related stuff. I’m going to write about my journey in search of my “almost perfect” editor.</p>

<p><img align="left" src="https://twobithistory.org/images/c64_startup.png" class="post-image align-post-image" alt="a commodore 64 shell" />  When I started doing some programming there wasn’t much of a choice. The C64 was offering one type of editing mode and nothing more so I didn’t bother much about it and the
same happened while in high school, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Olivetti_M24">Olivetti M24</a> and <a href="https://classic.technology/wp-content/uploads/2021/10/olivettim240german.pdf">Olivetti M240</a> had some really simple text editors not that different from C64 shell. In the end I got used to it and this probably why
I still find myself comfortable using the command line.
Not much to say about university years. I was studying electronics and not coding much. I also didn’t have a computer at home so I was using whatever was present on the University computers, from <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/JBuilder">JBuilder</a> to Notepad or <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Notepad%2B%2B">Notepad++</a>.</p>

<p>When I started professionally as a web developer, the first company I worked for was using ASP and provided me a desktop equipped with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Visual_InterDev">VisualInterDev</a>. The company then went bankrupt and I moved to another one where I really learned web development from scratch. Starting out with HTML/CSS and then, at the time, the next natural step was PHP. I then started developing with Java so I moved from <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PHPEdit">PHPEdit</a> to <a href="https://www.eclipse.org/downloads/">Eclipse</a> that became my preferred choice for both languages. Given the type of work required by the company, I also started getting used to FreeBSD servers and <a href="https://www.vim.org">Vim</a> as an editor for configuration files and small shell scripts.<br />
At that time I was freelancing and sometimes I had to code with programming languages chosen by the customer and thus the IDE choice by was not under my control. The list is long and I won’t mention all of them, just that that I had to use Delphi and PL/SQL :sweat:</p>

<p>The real change happened when I did two things after I’ve started working with a company building a web application using Ruby on Rails: I adopted Ubuntu as-my-day to day OS and started using <a href="https://github.com/aptana/studio3">Aptana RadRails</a>. Being that a small startup we also had to do some system administration on Ubuntu servers so Vim was the standard choice. However, those early version of Ubuntu weren’t that “user friendly” so I had frequently to use the command line and edit files. Constantly switching between editors became tiresome so I started looking for a more flexible alternative and while reading a book about early open source movement contributors, I’ve noticed that many of them were using <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Emacs">Emacs</a>, so I’ve installed it and started using it.
The beginning was hard, I had to learn all the basic concepts, how to navigate and edit files and more how to configure it for my purposes. But once I digested all this preliminary information and started getting used to it, the experience was highly satisfactory. I also discovered <a href="https://github.com/tmuxinator/tmuxinator">Tmuxinator</a>, a Ruby Gem that makes <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tmux">Tmux</a> session management easier, and using it together with Emacs was absolutely dope! I was finally able to configure my development environment in such a way that I could have different Tmux sessions opened for different projects with all that I need already in place.</p>

<p>That should have been my sweet spot; however, since I was still doing some sysadmin work, most of the times Vim was the only available editor and I then decided after 4 years of Emacs to finally move to <a href="https://www.lunarvim.org">Lunarvim</a>, a <a href="https://neovim.io">Neovim</a> based editor which comes by default with a lot of nice features. The only thing I had to configure was the code completion and the Golang support.</p>

<p>The search for my ‘Sacred Graal of Editors’ has been driven by my inherent laziness. I don’t want to change much some of my daily routines and constantly switching between IDEs while using different programming languages and while editing configuration files on some remote server was making me less productive. At the end what we need is a well ingrained muscle memory that keeps us productive and helps us getting the job done. Vim is ubiquitous and can be found in all Unix-like systems which means that I can just sit down and start coding.</p>

<p>At the end what makes difference is how comfortable are with your tools. If you prefer a comprehensive IDE that takes care of all the aspects of a developer’s workflow, just use it. IDEs will continue to improve, but I will persist with my tools, which may appear antiquated to some, but if you’re still trying to find your preferred editor, give Vim or Emacs a try, you won’t regret it.</p>

<p>Note: This post has been entirely written and edited on Lunarvim <img src="/images/downhand.gif" alt="a gif of a hand pointing down" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/lunarvim.png" class="post-image" alt="lunarvim welcome screen" /></p>

<hr />

<h4 id="things-i-like---in-random-order">Things I like - in random order</h4>

<p>Perseverance’s 360 view from Airey Hill - Original <a href="https://mars.nasa.gov/resources/27844/perseverances-360-degree-view-from-airey-hill/?utm_source=iContact&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_campaign=nasas-mars-public-engagement-team&amp;utm_content=20231220-MarsNewsletter-A">here</a>
<br />
<img src="/images/perseverance-airey-hill.jpg" alt="a 360 degrees of airey hill taken from perseverance mars rover" class="post-image" />
<br />
<br />
My Christmas tree - picture taken using one of Hipstamatic lenses 
<br />
<img src="/images/christmas-tree.jpeg" alt="the christmas tree in my living room with a instant camera filter" class="post-image" />
<br /></p>

<hr />

<h4 id="todays-links">Today’s Links</h4>

<p>Apple explores A.I. deals with some news publishers <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2023/12/22/technology/apple-ai-news-publishers.html">N.Y. Times</a></p>

<p>Britain is an ‘omni-surveillance society’ <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/uk-news/2023/oct/29/britain-omni-surveillance-society-watchdog-warns?utm_term=658531d6070054b93415af41a0313739&amp;utm_campaign=FirstEdition&amp;utm_source=esp&amp;utm_medium=Email&amp;CMP=firstedition_email">The Guardian</a></p>

<p>Police to be able to run <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2023/dec/20/police-to-be-able-to-run-face-recognition-searches-on-50m-driving-licence-holders">facial recognition</a></p>

<p>Building Future Mars <a href="https://mars.nasa.gov/news/9513/nasa-uses-two-worlds-to-test-future-mars-helicopter-designs/">Helicopters</a></p>

<p>Introducing Solid Queue - A DB-based queuing <a href="https://dev.37signals.com/introducing-solid-queue/">backend</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Wildeng</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In my last post I said that I wanted to be more technical and so be it. But in a different way and not “so technical”: I won’t talk about classes, methods, modules, mixin or some other Ruby related stuff. I’m going to write about my journey in search of my “almost perfect” editor.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A few misses</title><link href="https://alainmauri.eu/2023/12/17/a-few-misses/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A few misses" /><published>2023-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://alainmauri.eu/2023/12/17/a-few-misses</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alainmauri.eu/2023/12/17/a-few-misses/"><![CDATA[<p>It’s been a while since the last post but I had a couple of things that took me away from writing: A Christmas concert with the choir and my job which is highly demanding  in this period. More, I was finding difficult to find a good subject so I guess that sometimes is it ok to put out something that I found interesting? I guess so even if I’m not that sure about it, but at least it keeps the flow going.</p>

<p>I promise that the next one will be more interesting and probably more tech oriented.</p>

<p>In the meantime the question is: Will Ruby 3.3 be released on Christmas day? Fingers crossed :smile:</p>

<hr />

<h4 id="things-i-like---in-random-order">Things I like - in random order</h4>

<p>I love this <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/video-friday-floppybot">Floppy Bot</a></p>

<p>The iMac G3 is 25 years old. What a beautiful machine
<br />
<img src="/images/imac-g3-blue.jpg" alt="a blue apple imac g3" class="post-image" />
<br />
<br /></p>
<h5 id="some-ai-generated-images">Some AI generated images</h5>
<p>I’ve generated some images using the Canva Smart Image Generator<br />
Queen Elizabeth playing the guitar at Woodstock<br />
<br />
<img src="/images/Queen-Elizabeth-guitar.png" alt="an artificial intelligence generated image of queen elisabeth playing at Woodstock" class="post-image" />
<br />
<br />
A middle age software engineer - well they could be me<br />
<br />
<img src="/images/middle-age-engineer.png" alt="an artificial intelligence generated image of a middle age software engineer" class="post-image" />
<br /></p>

<hr />

<h4 id="todays-links">Today’s Links</h4>

<p>AI’s Climate Impact on the <a href="https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/ais-climate-impact-goes-beyond-its-emissions/">Scientific American</a></p>

<p>Is it possible to understand someone’s else mind <a href="https://www.technologyreview.com/2023/11/15/1083250/is-it-possible-to-really-understand-someone-elses-mind/">MIT Technology Review</a></p>

<p>The life and times of <a href="https://retool.com/pipes">Yahoo Pipes</a></p>

<p>COP28 Summit <a href="https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/cop28-climate-summit-deal-called-historic-now-countries-must-follow-through/">deal</a></p>

<p>Inventor of aircon helped chill NASA wind tunnels <a href="https://www.nasa.gov/centers-and-facilities/glenn/inventor-of-air-conditioning-helped-chill-nasa-wind-tunnels/">on NASA</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Wildeng</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It’s been a while since the last post but I had a couple of things that took me away from writing: A Christmas concert with the choir and my job which is highly demanding in this period. More, I was finding difficult to find a good subject so I guess that sometimes is it ok to put out something that I found interesting? I guess so even if I’m not that sure about it, but at least it keeps the flow going.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">To Feed or not Too Feed</title><link href="https://alainmauri.eu/2023/11/28/to-feed-or-not-to-feed/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="To Feed or not Too Feed" /><published>2023-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://alainmauri.eu/2023/11/28/to-feed-or-not-to-feed</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alainmauri.eu/2023/11/28/to-feed-or-not-to-feed/"><![CDATA[<p>Recently I started reading about the <a href="https://indieweb.org/?utm_source=ownyourweb&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_campaign=issue-03">Indie Web</a> movement, which is a people-focused alternative to the corporate owned one, and it really struck a chord.<br />
Principles like owning your content and being in control of what gets published are the things that got me started trying to understand how to build websites and to become a web developer.<br />
And after many years trying to use different platforms such as Wordpress, Medium, Dev etc. I went back to the most simple stuff: HTML, CSS and a simple RSS Feed - Atom to be honest.</p>

<p>Knowing the building blocks is something that every web developer should know before moving to other stuff like modern JS frameworks. It’s like Lego building, you cannot start from difficult Technic builds if you never experienced the barebone ones. More it unleashes your creativity, without boundaries and any kind of constraint or rules which are dictated by the framework used.<br />
This can easily be seen if you remember <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/19961226182558/http://www3.geocities.com/">Geocities</a> and compare the craziness of any of those websites - <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/19961221002840/http://www.geocities.com/Area51/4091/">Aden’s Boba Fett Page</a> for example - with the uniformity of styles that we have today and you would easily understand what I mean.<br />
I do appreciate the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">responsive design</code> and other modern features but to me, most of the web applications and websites are looking the same. Same colours, same icons, same fonts, same left side menu and toast messages. 
The corporate world definitely took over and we’re all doing stuff in the same way. We lost that primal spirit that drove the innovation, we lost the will to learn the building blocks, find your own way and have fun building something unique.<br />
Take a look at the job offers, they’re all looking the same - not talking about backend developers even though it is not much different - all looking for the same kind of developers, all looking for xyz framework, xyz years of experience etc.<br />
This means that if someone wants a job in this industry, the first thing they could possibly do is enrolling in a bootcamp that teaches the xyz framework, start building a small portfolio and eventually doing some job interviews.<br />
Nothing wrong with it, but you end up learning what the businesses need, skipping the basics.</p>

<p>From the web owned by a lot of people we transitioned to a web owned by a few, from a decentralised web to a centralised one. Most of the “new web” makes money by selling services or selling data such as age, gender, what of websites you visit, what kind of searches you do etc, to third parties that will then use them for some kind of business. Another way is by offering a platform where you can create content - think about Medium, Wattpad etc. - with revenues coming from subscription fees, data sold to third parties and advertisement. Now, think about the worst case: What happens if one of these platforms goes down and suffers a loss of data? What if one of these platforms file for bankruptcy and closes their servers or sells everything to some rogue company? You will probably lose most of your work without any chance to recover it.</p>

<p>Is there a solution to this?  Maybe, but there’s one thing I’m sure of: Owning your website is part of it. If you own your site you can decide what to publish, how to do it and when to do it. You will still need some hosting service to publish it but if that service has any kind of problem, you can simply move it somewhere else. Your personal website is all around the content you produce and not around the business model decided by the corporate company that owns the platform you are using and more, it’s a reflection of your personality, your choices and your personal taste.</p>

<p>The personal website is NOT dead, - just a bit forgotten - long live the personal website!</p>

<hr />

<h4 id="things-i-like---in-random-order">Things I like - in random order</h4>

<p><br />
<b>Space Jam original website</b>
<br />
<a href="https://www.spacejam.com/1996/jam.html" target="_blank" title="1996 Space Jam website§">
<img src="/images/space-jam-1996.jpg" alt="space jam 1996 website homepage still available online" class="post-image" />
</a>
<br />
<br />
Ganymede as seen from Juno - Nasa <a href="https://apod.nasa.gov/apod/">picture of the week</a>
<br />
<img src="/images/Ganymede2_JunoGill_960.jpg" alt="image of Ganymede as seen from Juno" class="post-image" />
<br />
<br />
<br /></p>

<hr />

<h4 id="todays-links">Today’s Links</h4>

<p>Barack Obama interviewed on AI, Free Speech and the future of technology <a href="https://youtu.be/X15o2sG8HF4?si=7EGxmmOHhDi-EC7e">YouTube</a></p>

<p>The Envy Office - how corporates are trying to lure employees back in the office by making them instagrammable - from the <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2023/11/26/business/office-design-rto.html?unlocked_article_code=1.B00.u1dg.ytttC4l3-02x&amp;smid=url-share">New York Times</a></p>

<p>Is <a href="https://neocities.org/browse">Neocities</a> the new Geocities?</p>

<p>I am on Neocities too <a href="https://wildeng.neocities.org">Wildeng</a></p>

<p>Publish (on your) Own Site, Syndicate Elsewhere <a href="https://indieweb.org/POSSE">POSSE</a></p>

<p>Probably one of the most influential minicomputers of all times <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2022/03/a-brief-tour-of-the-pdp-11-the-most-influential-minicomputer-of-all-time/">PDP11</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Wildeng</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Recently I started reading about the Indie Web movement, which is a people-focused alternative to the corporate owned one, and it really struck a chord. Principles like owning your content and being in control of what gets published are the things that got me started trying to understand how to build websites and to become a web developer. And after many years trying to use different platforms such as Wordpress, Medium, Dev etc. I went back to the most simple stuff: HTML, CSS and a simple RSS Feed - Atom to be honest.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">1991 What a Year!</title><link href="https://alainmauri.eu/2023/11/18/what-a-year/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="1991 What a Year!" /><published>2023-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://alainmauri.eu/2023/11/18/what-a-year</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alainmauri.eu/2023/11/18/what-a-year/"><![CDATA[<p>Personally it was quite an ordinary year, I didn’t have much time to study for the university because I was playing in a band and I didn’t have much time left. Honestly I was enjoying my time and not thinking too much about studying, but still doing a bit of programming on my C64c and exploring the UNIX mainframe of the University of Trieste IT department.</p>

<p>Rock Music was mainstream and big names - Metallica, Nirvana, REM, Extreme, Pearl Jam  where battling for number ones. So many good albums have been released that year from artists like Nirvana <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nevermind">Nevermind</a>, Metallica <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metallica_(album)">“Black Album”</a>, R.E.M. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Out_of_Time_(album)">Out of Time</a>, Guns’n’Roses <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Use_Your_Illusion_I">Use your Illusion I</a>  and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Use_Your_Illusion_II">Use your Illusion II</a>, Pearl Jam <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ten_(Pearl_Jam_album)">Ten</a>, RHCP <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blood_Sugar_Sex_Magik">Blood Sugar Sex Magik</a> and many others - e.g. Soundgarden, Stone Temple Pilots, Alice in chains etc.</p>

<h5 id="on-the-tech-side"><b>On the tech side</b></h5>
<p>On the 6th of August 1991 the first website <a href="http://info.cern.ch">info.cern.ch</a> ever was published by the Cern in Geneva and hosted on Tim Berners Lee’s NEXT computer and if I’m here throwing random words out in the wild is because of him and his work that changed the life of so many people around the world.</p>

<p>Linus Torvalds released the Linux Kernel to several Usenet Groups <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/History_of_Linux">Wikipedia</a></p>

<p>Apple <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PowerBook">PowerBook</a> series of laptop was introduced to the market</p>

<hr />

<h4 id="things-i-like---in-random-order">Things I like - in random order</h4>

<p>I do love all Beatles albums but my favourite one is <a href="https://album.link/i/1441164604">Sgt. Pepper’s Lonely Heart Club Band</a>
<br />
The Cray 1 supercomputer: Unfortunately I couldn’t use it but the Maths department of my university had it and I’ve been able to see it displayed in a room after its operational period was over. What a cool design it had!
<br />
<img src="/images/Cray1.jpg" alt="image of a Cray1 supercomputer in a red color in a room" class="post-image" />
<br />
<br />
<br />
Nasa celebrates astronaut’s Alan Shepard’s 100th birthday with the <a href="https://www.nasa.gov/image-detail/s63-02082orig/">picture of the week</a>
<br />
<img src="/images/alan-shepard.jpg" alt="image of astronaut Alan Shepard in a space suit" class="post-image" />
<br />
<br />
<br />
A picture I took in October 2016 in <a href="https://www.cividale.com/uk/santuario_di_castelmonte#">Castelmonte</a>
<br />
<img src="/images/castelmonte_october_2016.jpeg" alt="image of part of the walls of Castelmonte sanctuary taken in october 2016 with ivy turning red" class="post-image" /></p>

<hr />

<h4 id="todays-links">Today’s Links</h4>

<p>On Apple music <a href="https://music.apple.com/gb/playlist/rock-hits-1991/pl.0248cb21232d4f12bb823f234e2961e5">Rock Hits: 1991</a></p>

<p>From the CERN website <a href="https://home.web.cern.ch/science/computing/birth-web">The Birth of the Web</a></p>

<p>A nice article about <b>POSSE</b> - <i>Publish (on your) Own Site, Syndicate Elsewhere</i> from <a href="https://indieweb.org/POSSE?utm_source=ownyourweb&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_campaign=issue-02">David Pierce</a></p>

<p><b>Own your web</b> newsletter <a href="https://buttondown.email/ownyourweb">subscribe page</a></p>

<p>Naomi Klein on why wellness culture is embracing far-right theories: From the <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/books/2023/nov/15/naomi-klein-interview-wellness-culture-far-right">Guardian</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Wildeng</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Personally it was quite an ordinary year, I didn’t have much time to study for the university because I was playing in a band and I didn’t have much time left. Honestly I was enjoying my time and not thinking too much about studying, but still doing a bit of programming on my C64c and exploring the UNIX mainframe of the University of Trieste IT department.]]></summary></entry></feed>