<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-11-02T14:19:34+00:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Alain Mauri</title><subtitle>First draft of my new personal website</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Writing in a Rainy Day</title><link href="/2023/11/02/back-again/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Writing in a Rainy Day" /><published>2023-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2023/11/02/back-again</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/11/02/back-again/">&lt;p&gt;Today I’m writing from a soggy Sheffield and this is probably the right time to open the laptop and start thinking about what to say. Finding the right topics is not an easy task, especially for someone that’s not used to “common” writing - I do write a lot of code during the day though :smile: - and therefore I’m always scared of a blank page and that’s why I usually start by adding the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Things I like&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Today&apos;s links&lt;/code&gt;. But when the topic has been decided, well words flow smoothly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, the question is: Why did I go into web development?&lt;br /&gt;
TL;DR&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I went into web development because I loved the Internet since the first time I used it and I understood its potential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first computer was a C64c that my dad brought home when I was around twelve/thirteen years old and I was already reading some computer magazines that were available at that time, trying to understand whatever I could about the new cool stuff: Home Computers.&lt;br /&gt;
The next step naturally came: Reading the user manual and start developing small programs and so on. But because my family wasn’t that wealthy, in the years to come we couldn’t afford to buy more modern machine so the C64c was my only available home computer for a long time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been enough lucky that through my high school and then  my university I had access to different kinds of computers, from MS-DOS to Window based ones, Unix mainframes and Apple Macintosh, where I’ve been able to develop some really basic programming skills. Well not that basic, given that for my master thesis I built an Apache module with Pearl to serve the content of a website depending on the type of client. Sort of responsive web, but a bit earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The real change came when I graduated and a friend of mine asked me if I wanted to join his web development startup. I obviously accepted and on my first day I’ve been given a book about PHP and some time to learn. And here I am now…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A useful &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;git alias&lt;/code&gt; that gives you a nice and concise view of your commits&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;gpretty=&apos;git log --date=short --format=&quot;%C(blue)%h %C(reset)%s %C(magenta)%aN %C(green ul) %ad%C(reset)&quot;&apos;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A collection of &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;git&lt;/code&gt; commands on this &lt;a href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/wildeng/9d95eb31a5db17d5f13e9339f68496fe&quot;&gt;Gist&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/alain-c64c.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;a commodore c64c on a white table with a datasette connected to it&quot; class=&quot;post-image&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
My wonderful C64c - I&apos;m still using it
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;things-i-like---in-random-order&quot;&gt;Things I like - in random order&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do enjoy reading stuff on &lt;a href=&quot;https://substack.com/&quot;&gt;Substack&lt;/a&gt;, I found some really cool writers there. The ones I’m currently following are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The one and only &lt;a href=&quot;https://substack.com/@pattismith&quot;&gt;Patti Smith&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
Opinions from &lt;a href=&quot;https://substack.com/@robertreich&quot;&gt;Robert Reich&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
If I want to have a different view on books, music, arts etc. &lt;a href=&quot;https://substack.com/@tedgioia&quot;&gt;Ted Gioia&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
How cool is she? &lt;a href=&quot;https://substack.com/@margaretatwood&quot;&gt;Margaret Atwood&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finding new music on &lt;a href=&quot;https://bandcamp.com/&quot;&gt;Bandcamp&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Liverpool based artist &lt;a href=&quot;https://pixeymusic.bandcamp.com/album/dreams-pains-paper-planes&quot;&gt;Pixey&lt;/a&gt;
Some good Synthpop from &lt;a href=&quot;https://fm84.bandcamp.com/album/atlas&quot;&gt;FM-84&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What about the concept and design of &lt;a href=&quot;https://poolsuite.net/&quot;&gt;Poolsuite&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I :heart: this picture&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://apod.nasa.gov/apod/image/2310/WizardCenter_McInnis_960.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Halloween and the wizard nebula, picture of the day by Richard McInnis&quot; class=&quot;post-image&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;NASA Picture of the day &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find it here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://apod.nasa.gov/apod/ap231031.html&quot;&gt;Halloween and the Wizard Nebula&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;todays-links&quot;&gt;Today’s Links&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How cool is this? An PDF issue of &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Softalk&lt;/code&gt; an Apple II focused magazine of the early 80s: &lt;a href=&quot;https://vintageapple.org/softalk/pdf/SOFTALK_8009_v1_n01.pdf&quot;&gt;Softalk Sept. 1980&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the websites I love most: &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/&quot;&gt;Internet Archive&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some interesting considerations about web design:
&lt;a href=&quot;https://heather-buchel.com/blog/2023/10/why-your-web-design-sucks/&quot;&gt;It’s 2023, here is why your web design sucks.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NASA project to let members of the public collaborate with scientists &lt;a href=&quot;https://science.nasa.gov/citizen-science/&quot;&gt;Citizen Science&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Wildeng</name></author><summary type="html">Today I’m writing from a soggy Sheffield and this is probably the right time to open the laptop and start thinking about what to say. Finding the right topics is not an easy task, especially for someone that’s not used to “common” writing - I do write a lot of code during the day though :smile: - and therefore I’m always scared of a blank page and that’s why I usually start by adding the Things I like and Today&apos;s links. But when the topic has been decided, well words flow smoothly.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A New Start</title><link href="/2023/10/28/back-to-blogging/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A New Start" /><published>2023-10-28T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-10-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/2023/10/28/back-to-blogging</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/10/28/back-to-blogging/">&lt;p&gt;It’s been a while since last time I wrote a blog post about something. I do not know what happened but I had the feeling that it wasn’t worth doing it anymore.
I think that my expectations were so high that it’s been hard accepting the truth: In the world outside there are so many people writing about anything, and some of them
are so good, that my posts were just a drop in a vast ocean of information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that I’m in a sort of midlife crisis, I’ve decided to come back and try again, without any expectation. I’m here just because I feel the need to write about whatever goes through my mind, no limits, and I’ve decided to not use any kind of third party platform. It will all be hosted on my personal website, at the end this is what the Internet was meant to be isn’t it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My current tools are &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Lunarvim&lt;/code&gt; and I’m using &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Markdown&lt;/code&gt; to format the text more, I’m generating - through Jekyll - static &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;HTML&lt;/code&gt; pages and publish them using a shell script on &lt;b&gt;Github Pages&lt;/b&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
A bit of old school that makes writing more fun and more related to my job as a backend engineer, since I don’t have to change my “tools”. A bit lazy? Well, yes :smile:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also set up a goal for myself: One post each week and it doesn’t have to be a long one, but it must be worth my time. it could only be a bunch of links about interesting things that I found online or that I’ve read in some newsletter I’ve subscribed to, or memes or anything else.&lt;br /&gt;
This will be my personal space and I need to feel good and proud about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;things-i-like---in-random-order&quot;&gt;Things I like - in random order&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s been a couple of years now since singning up to Duolingo, but honestly I’ve only recently started to enjoy it. I’m currently trying to learn a bit of what I call survival skills in both German and French. I need the bare minimum, going to a supermarket and being able to buy groceries, talk to a taxi driver, ask for informations etc. I think that trying to express yourself in the local language shows appreciation to the country’s culture. As an Italian living in the UK I really appreciate when someone makes the effort to share some Italian words with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Music is what makes me happy and always will be. I cannot see my life without it and I do love playing my guitar, my bass and singing in the choir, it just makes me feel great.&lt;br /&gt;
I would like to have more time to invest in all these activities but I don’t, so I’m trying to enjoy every single bit of what I have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;:heart: Family, I have a great partner and two wonderful kids :heart: :smile:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A nice image I found on a wonderful fediverse profile &lt;a href=&quot;https://tech.lgbt/@mhzmodels&quot;&gt;MhzModels&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.tech.lgbt/media_attachments/files/111/301/458/192/796/183/original/74849cdcb74a45a5.png&quot; alt=&quot;Voxel render of a Commodore 64 computer, television, disk drive and WICO Command Control joystick. BASIC is displayed on the screen.&quot; class=&quot;post-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;todays-links&quot;&gt;Today’s Links&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found this in a newsletter called &lt;b&gt;Own your web&lt;/b&gt; and it’s a 1998 post from Tim Berners Lee: 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/Provider/Style/URI.html?utm_source=ownyourweb&amp;amp;utm_medium=email&amp;amp;utm_campaign=issue-01&quot;&gt;Cool URIs don’t change&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A nice post around a Ruby not that new feature: &lt;a href=&quot;https://zverok.space/blog/2023-10-20-syntax-sugar2-pattern-matching.html&quot;&gt;Pattern Matching&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why the so called “Tech Bros” are potentially dangerous: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2023/10/28/opinion/marc-andreessen-manifesto-techno-optimism.html?unlocked_article_code=1.6Uw.jmaL.VtOfnGERrmqK&amp;amp;smid=url-share&quot;&gt;Elizabeth Spiers on NY Times&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Wildeng</name></author><summary type="html">It’s been a while since last time I wrote a blog post about something. I do not know what happened but I had the feeling that it wasn’t worth doing it anymore. I think that my expectations were so high that it’s been hard accepting the truth: In the world outside there are so many people writing about anything, and some of them are so good, that my posts were just a drop in a vast ocean of information.</summary></entry></feed>